<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Representation learning on Desh Raj</title>
    <link>https://desh2608.github.io/tags/representation-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Representation learning on Desh Raj</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 13:39:15 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://desh2608.github.io/tags/representation-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Euclidean Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://desh2608.github.io/post/beyond-euclidean-embeddings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 13:39:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://desh2608.github.io/post/beyond-euclidean-embeddings/</guid>
      <description>Representation learning, as the name suggests, seeks to learn representations for structures such as images, videos, words, sentencences, graphs, etc., which may then be used for several objectives. Arguably the most important representations used nowadays are word embeddings, usually learnt using the distributional semantics methods such as skip-gram or GloVe. I have previously written about these methods here.
Two assumptions are inherent while using these methods to learn word vectors:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Word Vectors</title>
      <link>https://desh2608.github.io/post/understanding-word-vectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 11:12:55 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://desh2608.github.io/post/understanding-word-vectors/</guid>
      <description>This article is a formal representation of my understanding of vector semantics, from course notes and reading reference papers and chapters from Jurafsky’s SLP book. I will be talking about sparse and dense vector semantics, including SVD, skip-gram, and GloVe. In many places, I will try to explain the ideas in language rather than equations (but I’ll provide links to derivations and stuff wherever it is absolutely essential, which is actually everywhere!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>