<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Desh Raj</title>
    <link>https://desh2608.github.io/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Desh Raj</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 12:40:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://desh2608.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Text readability analysis using language modeling</title>
      <link>https://desh2608.github.io/project/readability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 17:01:44 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://desh2608.github.io/project/readability/</guid>
      <description>We conjecture that predictability of a text is a viable metric of its readability. By using modern language models as predictors, we believe this metric may provide an automated, fine-grained measure of readability. It also provides a natural mechanism to combine scores from different language models, and hence the ability to generalize to a diverse set of texts. Individual language models encode the specific linguistic background that a reader may have, hence providing customized scores for each type of reader.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relation extraction for clinical text</title>
      <link>https://desh2608.github.io/project/btp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 17:00:24 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://desh2608.github.io/project/btp/</guid>
      <description>The objective of the project was to devise a method for obtaining structured triplets from unstructured clinical records such as journal articles, patient health records etc. Simplifying this objective, I was tasked with creating a neural technique which can classify relations existing between entities in a given sentence, an NLP task known as relation classification.
The key insight is that convolutions can capture short-term phrases, while recurrence learns long-term dependencies. Combining both, we proposed the CRNN model which outperformed earlier single and double layer methods on two benchmark datasets: i2b2-2010 and DDI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Similarity analysis on multidimensional fuzzy sets</title>
      <link>https://desh2608.github.io/project/fuzzy-wmbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 17:01:05 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://desh2608.github.io/project/fuzzy-wmbs/</guid>
      <description>The objective of the project was to propose guidelines for selecting fuzzy membership functions to represent several data sets. In general, the accuracy of representation increases with increasing complexity, which makes it a trade-off. My contributions are listed below.
 Analyzed various multidimensional fuzzy membership functions and compared similarity of data sets using Wilcoxons nonparametric tests. Established guidelines for selecting appropriate MFs based on data set and application requirements. Recently extended the proposed method for high-dimensional data using dimensionality reduction approaches like PCA, kernel PCA, probabilistic PCA, and t-SNE.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>