<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>online learning on Desh Raj</title>
    <link>https://desh2608.github.io/tags/online-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in online learning on Desh Raj</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 13:40:57 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://desh2608.github.io/tags/online-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Learning of Word Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://desh2608.github.io/post/online-learning-word-embeddings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 13:40:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://desh2608.github.io/post/online-learning-word-embeddings/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Word vectors have become the building blocks for all natural language processing systems. I have earlier written an overview of popular algorithms for learning word embeddings &lt;a href=&#34;https://desh2608.github.io/post/understanding-word-vectors/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. One limitation with all these methods (namely SVD, skip-gram, and GloVe) is that they are all “batch” techniques. In this post, I will discuss two recent papers (which are very similar but were developed independently) which aim to provide an online approximation for the skip-gram algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But first, what do we mean by a “batch” algorithm?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, in a batch algorithm, the entire data set needs to be available before we begin the processing. In contrast, an “online” algorithm can process inputs on-the-fly, i.e., in a streaming fashion. Needless to say, such algorithms are also preferable when the available resources are not sufficient to process the entire dataset at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have some idea about batch algorithms, I’ll explain why the existing methods for word representation learning are of this kind. First, in the case of the standard SVD and Stanford’s GloVe, the entire cooccurence matrix needs to be computed, and only then can the processing be started. If some additional data arrives later, the matrix would have to be recomputed, and training would have to be restarted (if at least one of the updates depends on a changed matrix element). Second, in the case of Mikolov’s &lt;em&gt;word2vec&lt;/em&gt; (skip-gram and CBOW), negative sampling is often used to make the computation more efficient. This sampling depends on the unigram probability distribution of the vocabulary words in the corpus. As such, before learning can happen, we need to compute the vocabulary as well as the unigram distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, two very similar methods (developed independently) have been proposed to make the skip-gram with negative sampling (SGNS) algorithm learn in a streaming fashion. I’ll quickly review the SGNS algorithm first so that there is some context when we discuss the papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;batch-sgns-algorithm&#34;&gt;Batch SGNS algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://desh2608.github.io/img/15/skipgram.png&#34; alt=&#34;Skip-gram objective. Image taken from [The Morning Paper](https://blog.acolyer.org/2016/04/21/the-amazing-power-of-word-vectors/).&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SGNS is a window-based method with the following training objective: Given the target word, predict all the context words in the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have a context window where $w$ is the target word and $c$ is one of the context words. Then, skip-gram’s objective is to compute $P(c|w)$, which is given as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ p(c|w;\theta) = \frac{\exp(v_c \cdot v_w)}{\sum_{c^{\prime}\in C}\exp(v_{c^{\prime}}\cdot v_w)} $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it is just a softmax probability distribution over all the word-context pairs in the corpus, directed by the cosine similarity. However, the denominator term here is very expensive to compute since there may be a very large number of possible context words. To solve this problem, negative sampling is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goldberg and Levy have explained the derivation for the objective function in SGNS very clearly in their &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1402.3722.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;note&lt;/a&gt;. I will try to provide a little intuition here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the word $w$, we are trying to predict the context word $c$. Since we are using softmax, this is essentially like a multi-class classification problem, where we are trying to classify the next word into one of $N$ classes (where $N$ is the number of words in the dictionary). Since $N$ may be quite large, this is a very difficult problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What SGNS does is that it converts this multi-classification problem into binary classification. The new objective is to predict, for any given word-context pair $(w,c)$, whether the pair is in the window or not. For this, we try to increase the probability of a &amp;ldquo;positive&amp;rdquo; pair $(w,c)$, while at the same time reducing the probability of $k$ randomly chosen &amp;ldquo;negative samples&amp;rdquo; $(w,s)$ where $s$ is a word not found in $w$’s context. This leads to the following objective function which we try to maximize in SGNS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ J = \log \sigma(c\cdot w) + \sum_{i=1}^k \mathbb{E}_{w_i \sim p(w)}[\log \sigma (-w_i \cdot w)]  $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, we push the target vector in the direction of the positive context vector, and pull it away from $k$ randomly chosen (w.r.t. the unigram probability distribution) negative vectors. Here &amp;ldquo;negative&amp;rdquo; means that these vectors are not actually present in the target’s context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-do-we-need-to-make-sgns-online&#34;&gt;What do we need to make SGNS online?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is evident from the above discussion, since SGNS is a window-based approach, the training itself is very much in an online paradigm. However, the constraints are in creating a vocabulary and a unigram distribution for negative sampling, which makes SGNS a two-pass method. Further, if additional data is seen later, the distribution and vocabulary would change, and the model would have to be retrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, we need online alternatives for 2 aspects of the algorithms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic vocabulary building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adaptive unigram distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this background, I will now discuss the two proposed methods for online SGNS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;space-saving-word2vec&#34;&gt;Space-Saving word2vec&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1704.07463.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from researchers at Johns Hopkins, the following solutions were proposed for the two problems mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Space-saving algorithm for dynamic vocabulary building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reservoir sampling for adaptive unigram distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Space-saving algorithm:&lt;/strong&gt; It is a popular method to estimate the top-$k$ most frequent items in a streaming data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We declare a structure V containing $k$ pairs of word and their counts, and initialize it to empty pairs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As word $w$ arrives, if $w \in V$, we increment its count.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise, if $V$ has space, we append the pair $(w,1)$ to $V$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If not, the word with the lowest count is replaced by $w$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any instant, the words in the structure V denote the dynamic vocabulary of the corpus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reservoir sampling:&lt;/strong&gt; Reservoir sampling is a family of randomized algorithms for randomly choosing a sample of $k$ items from a list S containing $n$ items, where $n$ is either a very large or unknown number. (Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar to the SS algorithm, we declare a structure (called the reservoir) of $k$ empty elements (not pairs this time). In addition, we initialize a counter $c$ to 0.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first $k$ elements in the stream are filled into the reservoir. $c$ is incremented at every occurence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the remaining items, we draw $j$ from $1,\ldots,c$ randomly. If $j &amp;lt; k$, the $j^{\text{th}}$ element of the reservoir is replaced with the new element.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any instant, the samples present in the reservoir provide an approximate distribution of items in the entire data stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the algorithm itslelf is conceptually simple, the authors have mentioned several implementation choices which are important for training SGNS online. I list them here with some observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When a word is ejected from a bin in the dynamic vocabulary, its embeddings are re-initialized. As such, every bin has its own learning rate which is reset when the word in the bin is changed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During sentence subsampling, all words not in $W$ are retained. Those in $W$ are retained with a probability which is inversely proportional to the square root of its count in the dictionary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably the most important deviation from the SGNS algorithm is that the reservoir sampling essentially generates an empirical distribution from which to sample negative context words. In contrast, in the original SGNS algorithm, a &lt;em&gt;smoothed&lt;/em&gt; empirical distribution is used. The authors have themselves allowed that “ smoothing the negative sampling distribution was (sic) shown to increase word embedding quality consistently.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;incremental-sgns&#34;&gt;Incremental SGNS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;http://aclweb.org/anthology/D17-1037&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;EMNLP’17 paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from researchers at Yahoo Japan proposes the following alternative solutions for the aforementioned problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Misra-Gries algorithm for dynamic vocabulary building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A modified reservoir sampling algorithm for adaptive unigram table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misra-Gries algorithm:&lt;/strong&gt; This was developed long before the space-saving algorithm (1982) and was the go-to technique for top-$k$ most frequent itemset estimation in streaming data, before the space-saving algorithm was developed. The method is very similar to SS except for one difference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When word $w$ is not in $V$ and there is no space to append, every element in $V$ is decremented until some element becomes 0, at which point it is replaced by the new word.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modified reservoir sampling:&lt;/strong&gt; Here is the pseudocode from the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://desh2608.github.io/img/15/reservoir.png&#34; alt=&#34;Modified reservoir sampling. Image taken from original paper&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This algorithm differs from the conventional Reservoir Sampling in two important ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The counts used here are &lt;em&gt;smoothed&lt;/em&gt; (see line 4 to 6). This has been shown to be important for word vector quality, as discussed above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the reservoir does not have enough space, we iterate over all existing words and replace them with some probability (which is proportional to the smoothed count of $w$). Contrast this with the earlier technique, where a $j$ was randomly sampled and word at that index was replaced. (&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;I am not sure how exactly this modification helps in learning. If I am allowed to venture a guess, I would say that it is a “soft” equivalent of the hard replacement in the original algorithm. This probably helps in the theoretical analysis of the algorithm.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the authors have also provided theoretical justification for their algorithm and proved the following theorem: &lt;em&gt;The loss in case of incremental SGNS converges in probability to that of batch SGNS.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, SGNS is probably the easiest batch word embedding algorithm to “streamify” because of its inherent window-based nature. The constraints of vocabulary and counts are addressed with approximation algorithms. I can think of several possible directions in which this work can be continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, there are several algorithms for estimating the top-$k$ most frequent items in a data stream. These are divided into count-based and sketch-based methods. The SS algorithm is probably the most efficient count-based technique, but it may be useful to look at other methods to see if they provide some edge. (Although I’m pretty sure the JHU researchers would have been thorough in their
selection of the algorithm.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, GloVe and SVD are yet to be addressed. In case of GloVe in particular, the problem would be to construct the co-occurence matrix in a online fashion. There should be some related work in statistics which can be leveraged for this, but I haven’t conducted much literature survey in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;May, Chandler, Kevin Duh, Benjamin Van Durme, and Ashwin Lall. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Streaming word embeddings with the space-saving algorithm.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; arXiv preprint arXiv:1704.07463 (2017).
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Kaji, Nobuhiro, and Hayato Kobayashi. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Incremental skip-gram model with negative sampling.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; arXiv preprint arXiv:1704.03956 (2017).*
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sparsity in Online Learning with Lasso Regularization</title>
      <link>https://desh2608.github.io/post/sparse-online-learning-lasso-regularization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 13:40:42 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://desh2608.github.io/post/sparse-online-learning-lasso-regularization/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Sparse vectors have become popular recently for 2 reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sparse matrices require much less storage since they can be stored using various space-saving methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sparse vectors are much more interpretable than dense vectors. For instance, the non-zero non-negative components of a sparse word vector may be taken to denote the weights for certain features. In contrast, there is no interpretation for a value like $-0.1347$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sparsity is often induced through the use of L1 (or Lasso) regularization. There are 2 formulations of the Lasso: (i) convex constraint, and (ii) soft regularization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Convex constraint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name suggests, a convex constraint is added to the minimization problem so that the parameters do not exceed a certain value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ \min_{\beta \in \mathbb{R}^p}\lVert y - X\beta \rVert_2^2 \quad \text{s.t.} \quad \lVert \beta \rVert_1 \leq t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smaller the value of the tuning parameter $t$, fewer is the number of non-zero components in the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soft regularization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just the Lagrange form the the convex constraint, and is used because it is easier to optimize. Note that it is equivalent to the convex constraint formulation for an appropriately chosen $g$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ \min_{\beta \in \mathbb{R}^p}\lVert y - X\beta \rVert_2^2 + g\lVert \beta \rVert_1 $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a great theoretical explanation of sparsity with Lasso regularization by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.cmu.edu/~ryantibs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ryan Tibshirani&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.cmu.edu/~larry/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Larry Wasserman&lt;/a&gt; which you can find &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.cmu.edu/~larry/=sml/sparsity.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I will instead be focusing on some methods that have been introduced recently for inducing sparsity while learning online i.e., when the samples are obtained one at a time. In addition to such a scenario, online learning also comes into the picture when the data set is simply too large to be loaded in memory at once, and there are not sufficient resources for performing batch learning in a parallel fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will summarize 3 such methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume10/langford09a/langford09a.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Stochastic Truncated Gradient&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume10/duchi09a/duchi09a.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Forward Backward Splitting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mendeley.com/viewer/?fileId=00e458de-d9ca-a697-5d67-a4c177759778&amp;amp;documentId=0e9eba78-0cbb-3cb2-a8ea-385a2afb64f5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Regularized Dual Averaging&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, why a simple soft Lasso regularization won’t work? With the soft regularization method, we are essentially summing up 2 floating point values. As such, it is highly improbable that the sum will be zero, since very few pairs of floats add up to zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;stochastic-truncated-gradient-stg&#34;&gt;Stochastic Truncated Gradient (STG)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://desh2608.github.io/img/14/stg.png&#34; alt=&#34;Simple round-off (T0) vs. Truncated Gradient (T1). Image taken from paper&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STG combines ideas from 2 simple techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Coefficient rounding&lt;/em&gt;: In this method, the coefficients are rounded to 0 if they are less than a value $\theta$. This is denoted in the figure above (left graph). The rounding is done after every $k$ steps. The problem with this approach is that if $k$ is small, the coefficients do not get an opportunity to reach a value above $\theta$ before they are pulled back to $0$. On the other hand, if $k$ is large, the intermediate steps in the algorithm need to store a large number of non-zero coefficients, which does not solve the storage issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sub-gradient method&lt;/em&gt;: In this method, L1-regularization is performed by shifting the update in the opposite direction depending on the sign of the coefficient. The update equation is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ f(w_i) = w_i - \eta\nabla_1 L(w_i,z_i) - \eta g \text{sgn}(w_i) $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STG combines &lt;em&gt;rounding&lt;/em&gt; from (1) and &lt;em&gt;gravity&lt;/em&gt; from (2) so that (i) sparsity is achieved (unlike the sub-gradient method), and (ii) the rounding off is not too aggressive (unlike the direct rounding approach). The parameter update is then given by the function $T_1$ (shown in the right graph above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ T_1(v_j,\alpha,\theta) = \begin{cases} \max(0,v_j-\alpha) \quad &amp;amp;\text{if}~ v_j \in [0,\theta] \\\ \min(0,v_j+\alpha) \quad &amp;amp;\text{if}~ v_j \in [-\theta,0] \\\ 0 \quad &amp;amp;\text{otherwise}   \end{cases} $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The update rule is given using $T_1$ as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ f(w_i) = T_1 (w_i - \nabla_1 L_1 (w_i,z_i,\eta g_i,\theta)) $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, $g$ may be called the gravity parameter, and $\theta$ is called the truncation parameter. In general, the larger these parameters are, the more sparsity is incurred. This can be understood easily from the definition of the truncation function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, note that on setting $\theta = \infty$ in the truncation function yields a special case of the Sub-gradient method wherein &lt;strong&gt;max&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;min&lt;/strong&gt; operations are performed after applying gravity pull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the remainder of the paper, the authors prove a strong regret bound for the STG method, and also provide an efficient implementation for the same. Furthermore, they show the asymptotic solution of one instance of the algorithm is essentially equivalent to the Lasso regression, thus justifying the algorithm’s ability to produce sparse weight vectors when the number of features is intractably large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;forward-backward-splitting-fobos&#34;&gt;Forward Backward Splitting (FOBOS)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: The method was named Forward Looking Subgradient (FOLOS) in the first draft and later renamed since it was essentially the same as an earlier proposed technique, the Forward Backward Splitting. The authors abbreviated it to FOBOS instead of FOBAS to avoid confusing readers of the first draft.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a little background. Consider an objective function of the form $f(w) + r(w)$. In the case of a number of machine learning algorithms, the function $f$ denotes the empirical sum of some loss function (such as mean squared error), and the function $r$ is a regularizer (such as Lasso). If we use a simple gradient descent technique to minimize this objective function, the iterates would be of the form&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ w_{t+1} = w_t - \eta_t g_t^f - \eta_t g_t^r $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where the $g$’s are vectors from the subgradient sets of the corresponding functions. From the paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common problem in subgradient methods is that if $r$ or $f$ is non-differentiable, the iterates of the subgradient method are very rarely at the points of non-differentiability. In the case of the Lasso regularization function, however, these points are often the true minima of the function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the subgradient approach will result in neither a true minima nor a sparse solution if $r$ is the L1 regularizer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FOBOS, as the name suggests, splits every iteration into 2 steps — a forward step and a backward step, instead of minimizing both $f$ and $r$ simultaneously. The motivation for the method is that for L1 regularization functions, true minima is usually attained at the points of non-differentiability. For example, in the 2-D space, the function resembles a Diamond shape and the minima is obtained at one of the corner points. Each iteration of FOBOS consists of the following 2 steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ w_{t+\frac{1}{2}} = w_t - \eta_t g_t^f \\\ w_{t+1} = \text{argmin}_w { \frac{1}{2}(w_t - w_{t+\frac{1}{2}})^2 + \eta_{t+\frac{1}{2}}r(w) } $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is a simple unconstrained subgradient step with respect to the function $f$. In the second step, we try to achieve 2 objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay close to the interim update vector. This is achieved by the first term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attain a low complexity value as expressed by $r$. (Second term)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first step is a &lt;em&gt;forward&lt;/em&gt; step, where we update the coefficient in the direction of the subgradient, while the second is a &lt;em&gt;backward&lt;/em&gt; step where we pull the update back a little so as to obtain sparsity by moving in the direction of the non-differentiable points of $r$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the first equation in the second, taking derivative w.r.t $w$, and equating the derivative to $0$, we obtain the update scheme as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ w_{t+1} = w_t - \eta_t g_t^f + \eta_{t+\frac{1}{2}} g_{t+1}^r $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The equation above looks suspiciously similar to the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nesterov Accelerated Gradient (NAG)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; method for optimization. The authors have even cited Nesterov’s paper in related work. It might be interesting to  investigate this further.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This update scheme has 2 major advantages, according to the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, from an algorithmic standpoint, it enables sparse solutions at virtually no additional computational cost. Second, the forward-looking gradient allows us to build on existing analyses and show that the resulting framework enjoys the formal convergence properties of many existing gradient-based and online convex programming algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the paper, the authors also prove convergence of the method and show that on setting the intermediate learning rate properly, low regret bounds can be proved for both online as well as batch settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;regularized-dual-averaging-rda&#34;&gt;Regularized Dual Averaging (RDA)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of the above discussed techniques have one limitation — they perform updates depending only on the subgradients at a particular time step. In contrast, the RDA method “exploits the full regularization structure at each iteration.” Also, since the authors derive closed-form solutions for several popular optimization objectives, it follows that the computational complexity of such an approach is not worse than the methods which perform updates only based on current subgradients (both being $\mathcal{O}(n)$).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RDA comprises of 3 steps in every iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first step, the subgradient is computed for that particular time step. This is the same as every other subgradient-based online optimization method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second step consists of computing a running average of all past subgradients. This is done using the online approach as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ \bar{g}_t = \frac{t-1}{t}\bar{g}_{t-1} + \frac{1}{t}g_t $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third step, the update is computed as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ w_{t+1} = \text{argmin}_w { &amp;lt;\bar{g}_t,w&amp;gt; + \psi(w) + \frac{\beta}{t}h(w) } $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us try to understand this update scheme. First, the function $h(w)$ is a strongly convex function such that the update vector which minimizes it also minimizes the regularizer. In the case of Lasso regularization, $h(w)$ is chosen as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ h(w) = \frac{1}{2}\lVert w \rVert_2^2 + \rho \lVert w \rVert_1 $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $\rho$ is a parameter called the sparsity enhancing parameter. $\beta$ is a predetermined non-negative and non-decreasing sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to solve the equation, we can just take the derivative of the argument of argmin and equate it to $0$. On solving this equation, we get an update of the form&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$ w_{t+1} = \frac{t}{\beta_t}(\bar{g}_t + \rho) $$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the scheme ensures that the update is in the same convex space as the regularized dual average. Sparsity can further be controlled by tuning the value of the parameter $\rho$. The scaling factor can be regulated using the
non-decreasing sequence selected at the beginning of the algorithm. For the case when it is equal to the time step $t$, the new coefficient is simply the sum of the dual average and the sparsity parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is just my attempt at understanding the update scheme for RDA. I would be happy to discuss it further if you find something wrong with this explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the method itself would become extremely infeasible if this differentiation would have to be performed for every iteration. However, for most commonly used regularizers and loss functions, the update rule can be represented with a closed-form solution. For this reason, the overall algorithm has the same complexity as earlier algorithms which use only the current step subgradient for performing updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Langford, John, Lihong Li, and Tong Zhang. “Sparse online learning via truncated gradient.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Machine Learning Research&lt;/em&gt; 10.Mar (2009): 777–801.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Duchi, John, and Yoram Singer. “Efficient online and batch learning using forward backward splitting.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Machine Learning Research&lt;/em&gt; 10.Dec (2009): 2899–2934.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Xiao, Lin. “Dual averaging methods for regularized stochastic learning and online optimization.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Machine Learning Research&lt;/em&gt; 11.Oct (2010): 2543–2596.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
